The next section in the text is secondary hemostasis and related disorders,
and just as we did in the prior section, we first want to cover a little bit of normal before we go into the disorders.
Let's remind ourselves that the goal of secondary hemostasis is to stabilize the weak platelet plug,
and that occurs via the coagulation cascade.
Remember that when we formed the plug, let's go back and remind ourselves that this is the area of vessel damage.
We're going to have von Willebrand's factor coming in,
and then, of course, the platelet is going to adhese via GP1B binding to von Willebrand's factor.
And then beyond that, the next step would be, after release of the mediators,
will be that the platelets will then aggregate, a whole bunch of platelets will aggregate,
using the receptor called GP2B3A.
And remember that the cross-linking molecule that allows for that aggregation,
all the platelets to join together, this molecule is called, right here,
is called fibrinogen.
And fibrinogen is important because it is the area that the coagulation cascade is going to work on.
What I mean by that is this platelet plug is weak,
and what happens is the coagulation cascade generates something called thrombin.
The end product of the coagulation cascade is the generation of thrombin.
Thrombin comes in and converts fibrinogen to fibrin.
When fibrin is produced, fibrin can then be cross-linked to stabilize this interaction,
so that the end product of this entire cascade would then be the production of something called the platelet fibrin thrombus.
Platelet because platelets are the key cell here,
and fibrin because the final cross-linked product is a derivative of fibrin.
So this entire thing now becomes a stable platelet fibrin thrombus.
And remember that thrombus is just the band-aid that is used to cover the area of disruption of the blood vessel.
And so I say that here in your text by saying that the coagulation cascade generates thrombin.
This converts fibrinogen in the platelet plug to fibrin,
and then fibrin is then cross-linked, yielding the final platelet fibrin thrombus.
Now remember that the factors of the coagulation cascade,
they're actually produced by the liver in an inactive state.
They float around in the blood until eventually they get activated.
Activation requires a few things.
It requires exposure to an activating substance,
and I'll talk a little bit more about that in a couple slides.
It requires a phospholipid surface, and I can ask you a question here,
so where is the phospholipid surface coming from?
The answer is the surface of the platelets.
Remember that what this entire reaction is occurring,
basically I'm overdrawing this with these receptors being very big,
but the platelets are huge,
and this entire interaction is occurring basically on the surface of the platelets.
And finally, calcium is also essential,
and calcium is derived from the platelets.
Remember that the dense core granules contain calcium.
Now in disorders of secondary hemostasis,
it's usually going to be a problem of factor abnormalities because, of course,
the whole process of secondary hemostasis is dependent on all these factors which lead to the eventual production of thrombin.
And so the disorders of secondary hemostasis are usually going to be due to problems with factor amount, for example.
Now the clinical features of secondary hemostasis are going to be deep bleeding.
They get deep tissue bleeding into muscle and joints.
Now remember that in primary hemostasis, the key problem was skin and mucosal bleeding,
and skin and mucosa are superficial surfaces.
But this is deep tissue bleeding, like into muscles and joints.
And they can also get re-bleeding after surgical procedures.
So these are, for example, wisdom tooth extraction, just as an example.
And so these are some of the classic clinical findings in problems of secondary hemostasis.
Now, of course, because we've got disruption of the coagulation factors in these particular disorders,
the most useful laboratory study will be to study the different pathways.
And so we can look at the PT, which measures both the extrinsic pathway and the common pathway,
and we can measure the PTT, which measures the intrinsic pathway and the common pathway.
Now here what I like to do is stop for a moment and just remind you of the normal coagulation pathways.
I know that this is one of the biggest headaches for medical students to try to have to memorize this pathway,
but it's actually very easy if you just have a couple simple ways of remembering it.
So let me just tell you that the goal of the coagulation cascade is to produce the factor X.
It's kind of like the old Olympics.
I know they don't do this anymore in the Olympics, but it used to be that you wanted to produce the perfect 10.
So the goal of this entire pathway is to produce the perfect 10.
Now on this side, basically we're going to start at 12.
So we'll go 12, 11, skip 10, because we want to make that 9, 8.
All right, 12, 11, skip 10, 9, 8, 10, and then 7, because we're going to 7, 8, 9, skip 10, 11, 12, going the other way.
So again, just from left to right, 12, 11, skip 10, 9, 8, 10 is there,
and put 7 on the right-hand side.
So this then represents my two separate pathways,
and of course then the generation beneath that will be the common pathway,
and so this will be 5, 2, and 1.
And the way I remember that is 5 times 2 is 10, or you can say 1 times 2 times 5 is 10.
All right, and so you can work your way up towards the number 10.
So 10 becomes a very important number in trying to remember this pathway.
Of course, you don't have all the details here, but at least this gets you started.
Now a few important things to remember just based on this.
First of all, I can ask you a simple question.
You know, which side, this side or this side has more numbers?
And you clearly see that this left side has more numbers,
and so therefore when we want to measure the left side,
we're going to measure it with the one that has more letters.
So the PTT actually measures this particular side of the pathway,
and the PT measures this particular side of the pathway.
Another important point to recognize is that in the intrinsic pathway,
which is here on the left-hand side,
the key factor that gets activated first is factor 12,
and what activates factor 12 is subendothelial collagen.
So subendothelial collagen activates factor 12.
And if you look on the right-hand side,
which this right-hand side represents the extrinsic pathway,
then the key thing that activates factor 7 is tissue thromboplastin.
And notice again, this is easy for me to remember
when I don't memorize these things.
I'm just sitting here talking about, again, the top of my head,
and again, I just remember more numbers,
so I use PTT, and PTT has three letters,
so the subendothelial collagen,
which also has three letters,
is going to be the activator on this side.
And on this side, I remember PT, which has two letters.
Well, I know it's PT because it's not the PTT,
and there's two letters there,
so tissue thromboplastin also has two letters.
That's what helps me to remember this.
The other thing to remember is the fact that
which one of these two measurements, PT or PTT,
is better when you give heparin,
and which one is more useful when you give coumadin or warfarin,
which helps to inhibit both of these pathways.
Now, the idea here is remember that
one is better to measure the heparin effect,
and one is better to measure the coumadin effect.
And so the way I remember this is that PTT has three letters,
and when you walk around on the floors,
you're going to talk about heparin as hep,
and so PTT is the better measure for the heparin effect.
If you want to see what's going on
after you give the patient heparin,
the PTT is a better measure of that.
And therefore, the opposite would be
that the coumadin effect is better measured by the PT.
So that's some of the ways that I keep
this crazy different pathways in my mind,
and I hate memorizing,
so I've always got to have some funny way to do it.
Now let's go back and study the first disorder,
and that's hemophilia A.
This is a genetic defect in factor VIII.
All right?
That's important.
So you've got a factor VIII deficiency,
and it's funny when I'm sitting with my students,
hemophilia, forget about hemophilia A,
let's call it hemophilia VIII, VIII, okay?
So that A sticks in your mind there.
Funny way to do it, but whatever works.
So hemophilia VIII, all right?
This is an X-linked recessive disorder,
predominantly affects males because it's X-linked,
and can arise from a new mutation
without any family history.
So it's not uncommon in this disorder
to get de novo mutations
where you don't have a family history,
but the disorder arises all of a sudden de novo
in one of the offspring.
So that's important to note.
You don't need to always have a family history.
That's what I'm trying to highlight here.
Now, these patients have a factor VIII deficiency,
so they're going to present with deep tissue joint
and post-surgical bleeding.
These are the classic signs and symptoms
of patients who have disorders with secondary hemostasis.
The clinical severity will depend
on the degree of deficiency.
If there's a heavy deficiency or a major deficiency,
of course, it would be more clinically severe.
As far as laboratory findings are concerned,
there's going to be an increase in the PTT
and a normal PT.
So let's go back and remind ourselves,
if we just draw my little coagulation cascade,
we know we start with 12, and then we go to 11,
and we have to skip 10.
So we're going to go to 9, we're going to go to 8,
and then we're going to go to 7 up here,
and we're going to put 10 down here.
So when we're thinking about these two sides,
remember that this left side has more numbers,
so we're going to measure this with the PTT,
and this side, the right side, has fewer numbers,
so we're going to measure that with the PT, correct?
And when we think about the fact that in hemophilia A,
we've got an 8 deficiency,
so we're going to knock out 8,
and if we knock out 8, the PTT is going to go up.
In addition, when you have a prolonged PTT,
you're then going to measure the factor 8 levels,
and the factor 8 levels will clearly be down.
Now remember that there's no effect on the platelets here,
so the platelet count will be normal.
The bleeding time, where it to be measured classically,
would be normal as well.
So what's the treatment?
You simply give back the patient recombinant factor 8,
and of course that makes up for the deficiency.
Now in the next disorder, hemophilia B,
all we do is go one step back,
and instead of having a factor 8 deficiency,
we actually have a factor 9 deficiency.
This is also called Christmas disease, by the way.
And so the idea here is you've got 12, 11,
we skip 10, 9, 8, and then we put 7 over here,
and of course 10 is here.
So instead of having a factor 8 deficiency,
we kind of go one step back,
and now we've got a factor 9 deficiency,
and that's hemophilia B.
All right, so a genetic factor 9 deficiency.
Now clinically, it's going to resemble hemophilia A, right?
Because it's the exact same pathway,
you're just one step above.
So the only difference will be that
instead of having a decrease in factor 8 levels,
you're going to have a decrease in factor 9 levels.
So the factor 9 levels would actually be decreased in this disorder.
Another disorder of secondary hemostasis is for a patient to develop a coagulation factor inhibitor.
Now this is when they get an acquired antibody against a coagulation factor,
which then results in impairment of that factor function,
because if you've got an antibody blocking the factor,
the factor can't participate in the coagulation cascade.
And the most common coagulation factor inhibitor is an anti-factor 8.
So it's very similar to hemophilia 8, right?
Or hemophilia A.
Because in hemophilia A, you didn't have factor 8,
and in a coagulation factor inhibitor,
you have an antibody against factor 8,
which doesn't let factor 8 function.
Now how are you going to make that distinction?
Well clinically, and on lab findings,
you're going to have the same findings in both hemophilia A
and in a coagulation factor inhibitor.
But basically in both of these cases,
you're going to have an increase in the PTT.
And you're going to have similar clinical findings.
The way by which you're going to make the distinction
is by doing something called a mixing study.
And this becomes very high yield for examination purposes.
When you do a mixing study,
what you do is you take normal plasma
and you mix it with the patient's plasma.
If you take normal plasma and mix it with the patient's plasma
and the patient has hemophilia A,
then by giving the normal plasma,
you're going to give back some factor 8
and that's sufficient enough to reduce the PTT
and so to make it go back to normal.
And so you can actually correct the PTT
by mixing in normal plasma
with the patient's plasma in hemophilia A.
However, in the case of a coagulation factor inhibitor,
you're not going to be able to correct it
because as soon as you add the patient's normal plasma,
there's so much antibody against factor 8
that the antibody will, again, bind the normal,
the factor 8 that's coming from the normal plasma
and you won't be able to correct the PTT.
So the mixing study would fail
when there is a coagulation factor inhibitor.
And this is a very high yield distinction to be made here.
So that's important to bear in mind.
The next of the disorders that we want to discuss
is von Willebrand's disease
and this is a genetic defect in von Willebrand's factor.
This is the most common inherited coagulation disorder.
So that's very high yield.
It's high yield to know that.
It's also high yield to know this disorder.
Multiple subtypes exist.
We're not going to go into that level of detail here,
but we can have qualitative or quantitative defects
with von Willebrand's factor.
We're only going to talk about the most common type.
In the most common type, which is autosomal dominant,
you get decreased levels of von Willebrand's factor.
Now that decreased levels of von Willebrand's factor
is going to result in a problem with platelet adhesion, correct?
Because remember that when you've got
that exposed subendothelial collagen with the initial injury,
you've got von Willebrand's factor,
and von Willebrand's factor acts as a linker molecule
for the platelet to adhese using GP1B.
So if you don't have von Willebrand's factor,
that initial step of platelet adhesion can't occur,
which is going to disrupt primary hemostasis.
And so these patients are going to present
with mild mucosal and skin bleeding, right?
These are the signs of primary hemostasis
as we talked about in the prior section.
Again, I've explained why.
What will the laboratory findings be?
Well, there'll be an increased bleeding time
were that to be performed.
And again, that would be because
you don't have good platelet adhesion,
and if you don't have good platelet adhesion,
you're not going to be able to seal off
a damaged blood vessel quickly.
And so instead of bleeding,
the normal bleeding time being
anywhere from two to seven minutes,
it'll be prolonged,
maybe 10 minutes or 15 minutes, for example.
What's also interesting in this particular disorder
is that the PTT is going to be up.
And the reason why the PTT is going to be up
is because you need your von Willebrand's factor
to be able to stabilize factor VIII.
And so that's a high-yield principle to be aware of.
Von Willebrand's factor helps in stabilizing factor VIII.
And if you don't have von Willebrand's factor,
you're going to lose stability of factor VIII,
and that's going to increase the PTT.
Now, again, it increases the PTT
because you've got 12, 11, skip 10, 9, 8,
put 7 here, 10 here,
because that's the final goal of both pathways.
And again, if you've got a disruption of VIII,
this has more numbers on this side,
so the PTT is then going to be prolonged.
Now, it so happens that although the PTT is prolonged,
these patients generally don't get problems
with secondary hemostasis.
So there's enough of a lack of stability of factor VIII
that it will change the labs and increase the PTT,
but there is not enough of a lack of stability
to create clinical problems.
So it doesn't lead to clinical problems.
Of course, the PT would be normal.
Perhaps the most important laboratory finding
to be aware of in von Willebrand's disease
is an abnormal Ristocetin test.
The idea here is that if you were to put,
if you were to introduce Ristocetin
to the patient's platelets,
just normal platelets
that have normal von Willebrand's factor as well,
then what would happen is that the Ristocetin
would cause the platelets to all aggregate together.
In this particular case,
because the patient is lacking von Willebrand's factor,
which is necessary for that initial step of adhesion,
you won't be able to have the platelets
all aggregate together.
And so the Ristocetin test will be abnormal,
and that's particularly high yield in this discussion.
Now the treatment is desmopressin.
That's very high yield.
That goes back to pharmacology.
The mechanism is also high yield.
The mechanism by which desmopressin works
is that it increases the release
of von Willebrand's factor
from the Weibol-Pilotti bodies.
Now there's no rocket science here.
I've already explained this to you.
Remember that the Weibol-Pilotti bodies
are the bodies present in the endothelial cells
that you'd see on electron microscopy.
I reminded you several times in the past
that the W reminds me
that they contain von Willebrand's factor,
and the P reminds me
that they also contain P-selectin.
And we talked about P-selectin
in the inflammation chapter.
So basically here,
all you have to remember
is that desmopressin induces release
of von Willebrand's factor
from the Weibol-Pilotti bodies.
Another problem of secondary hemostasis
can arise with vitamin K deficiency.
Remember that vitamin K is necessary
for gamma-carboxylation of factors 2, 7, 9, 10, C, and S.
This is something you have to burn in your brain.
It shows up on every exam.
So you need to be able
to gamma-carboxylate factors 2, 7, 9, 10, C, S.
And vitamin K is essential
for being able to gamma-carboxylate those factors.
And remember that vitamin K
is activated by epoxide reductase in the liver.
So vitamin K comes in through the gut.
It goes to the liver.
It gets activated by epoxide reductase.
Once it's activated,
it can then gamma-carboxylate factors 2, 7, 9, 10, C, and S.
And just as a farm reminder,
remember that Coumadin,
the way by which it works
is that it actually blocks epoxide reductase.
If epoxide reductase is blocked,
vitamin K can't be activated.
And if vitamin K can't be activated,
then factors 2, 7, 9, 10, C, and S.
can't be gamma-carboxylated
and hence won't function properly.
Now vitamin K deficiency
is a little bit interesting
and goes back to a little bit of biochemistry.
Remember that vitamin K
is essentially generated by the bacteria in our gut.
And so the patients who get deficient
are going to have some sort of abnormality
of either the bacteria in the gut
or the ability to take up vitamin K.
For example, newborns,
their gut is not yet colonized by bacteria.
And so because they have a lack of GI colonization,
they are particularly susceptible
to getting problems of vitamin K deficiency-related bleeding.
And that's why at birth,
one of the injections that we give a baby,
a newborn at birth,
is we prophylactically give all newborns
when they're born vitamin K.
We give them vitamin K
to avoid hemorrhagic disease of the newborn.
So that's one example.
Another example would be long-term antibiotic therapy.
The idea here,
if you have long-term antibiotic therapy,
you're killing off the gut flora.
And as you kill off the gut flora,
again, you're not going to be able to generate vitamin K.
And then finally, malabsorption.
Remember that vitamin K is a fat-soluble vitamin.
And so if you don't have good absorption,
you won't be taking up your fat-soluble vitamins,
for example.
And so vitamin K, vitamin A, E, D,
these are the other ones,
A, E, D, and K
are the four key fat-soluble vitamins.
And so malabsorption could result in a vitamin K deficiency,
especially if there's fat malabsorption.
Finally, liver failure can also cause
a secondary hemostatic problem.
And the reason why is because
the vast majority of the coagulation factors
are made in the liver.
That's the first reason.
The second reason why is because epoxide reductase,
which was what activated vitamin K,
is also present in the liver.
So that would fail.
So basically, when you get liver failure,
there's two reasons why you're going to get
secondary hemostatic problems.
One, you're not producing factors.
And two, even if you're producing factors,
they're not getting secondarily activated
because epoxide reductase can't activate vitamin K.
And then if you don't have that activation of vitamin K,
then 2, 7, 9, 10, C, and S won't function properly.
Now, when you have liver failure,
it's important to remember that the key way
by which you measure the effect of liver failure
on coagulation is using the PT.
So the PT is the way by which you follow
the effect of liver failure on coagulation.
Large-volume transfusions are the very last thing
that we're going to discuss.
When you give a large-volume transfusion,
you're diluting out the coagulation factors
until you get a relative deficiency
of the coagulation factors,
which can also cause a disorder of secondary hemostasis.
So that closes off our section.
Again, not complicated.
It's most important to remember the normal.
Once you remember the normal,
then there's a few very simple principles
to derive from that,
which again then will help you to understand
most of the disorders in this section.